## James Higginson MA(Cantab) MB BChir BDS MRCSEd

Department of Surgery & Cancer Faculty of Medicine Imperial College London SW<sub>7</sub> 2AZ

Phone: 07789 954626

Email: j.higginson19@imperial.ac.uk url: https://www.higginsonsurgical.com

### Current position

Clinical Doctoral Fellow, Department of Surgery and Cancer, Imperial College London

### Memberships and Registration

Membership	Number
General Medical Council	7016858
General Dental Council	258556
Medical Protection Society	376166
British Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons	2682
European Head and Neck Society	2869
British Association of Head and Neck Oncologists	924
European Association of Craniomaxillofacial Surgeons	6883

### Grants, Awards and Honours

2018

2012

BAOMS Research Grant—£10,000 awarded for research into lipidomics of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma, in collaboration with the Institute of Head and Neck Cancer Studies and Education and the Phenome Centre Birmingham. Distinction Year 2 BDS—Awarded for excellence in examinations related to craniofacial biology and development.

I

### Qualifications

BDS, Newcastle University.

MRCSEd, Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh.

MB BChir, Cambridge Clinical School.

BA(Hons), later MA(Cantab), Fitzwilliam College Cambridge.

### Appointments Held

ACADEMIC AND MANAGEMENT APPOINTMENTS

2020- Deputy Lead, British Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons (BAOMS)

Reconstruction Subspecialty Interest Group.

<sup>2019–</sup> Clinical PhD Candidate, Imperial College London.

Trainee member, National Cancer Research Institute (NCRI) Head and Neck Re-

search Group.

2019- Trainee member, NCRI Head and Neck Surgery and Localised Therapies Sub-

group.

2016-2019 NIHR Academic Clinical Fellow, Institute of Head and Neck Studies and Educa-

tion (InHANSE), University of Birmingham.

Director, OpenOdontoHub, A Community Interest Company supported by NHS

England for the development of open-source electronic dental health record soft-

ware

Junior Trainee & Members Representative, BAOMS Council.

2014–2015 President, BAOMS Junior Trainee Group.

2013–15 Journal Club Section Editor, Face Mouth and Jaw Surgery, providing educational

analyses of papers for the international trainee journal of OMFS until its closure.

Treasurer, BAOMS Junior Trainee Group.

<sup>2009–2010</sup> Treasurer, Sunderland Royal Hospital Doctors' Mess.

#### CLINICAL APPOINTMENTS

2019- Clinical Doctoral Fellow, Queen Victoria Hospital, East Grinstead.

2018–2019 OMFS Specialty Trainee, University Hospitals Birmingham.

2017–2018 OMFS Specialty Trainee, Worcester Royal Hospital.

2016–2017 OMFS Specialty Trainee, University Hospitals Birmingham.

2015–2016 OMFS Trust Doctor, Sunderland Royal Hospital.

2011–2015 Emergency Medicine Staff Grade, South Tyneside District Hospital.

2010–2011 Core Surgical Trainee, Hull & East Yorkshire Hospitals.

Foundation Trainee, Sunderland Royal Hospital.

### **Publications**

Summary of total number of publications to date...

#### FULL MANUSCRIPTS

2020

2019

2018

2018

2015

2011

2020

2018

2018

Chouhan, R., Higginson, J. and Martin, T. 'Confidential Image Transfer: An Ethico-Legal Dilemma'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 58, no. 4 (May 2020): 478-80.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2020.02.013.

Borsetto, D., Higginson, J. (Joint first authors), Aslam, A., Al-Qamachi, L., Dhanda, J., Marioni, G., Franchella, S., et al. 'Factors Affecting Prognosis in Locoregional Recurrence of Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma'. Journal of Oral Pathology & Medicine 48, no. 3 (March 2019): 206-13. doi:10.1111/jop.12815.

Higginson, J.A., Bartram, A.C., Banks, R.J. and Keith, D.J.W., 'Condylar Hyperplasia: Current Thinking'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 8 (October 2018): 655–62.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.07.017.

Zavattini, A., Mancini, M., Higginson, J., Foschi, F., Pasquantonio, G. and Mangani, F., 'Micro-Computed Tomography Evaluation of Microleakage of Class II Composite Restorations: An in Vitro Study'. European Journal of Dentistry 12, no. 03 (July 2018): 369-74. doi:10.4103/ejd.ejd\_28\_18.

Acknowledged for statistical analysis—Banks, J., Adams, S, Laughlan, K., Allgar, V., Miller, G., Jayagopal, V., Gale, R., Sedman, P. and Leveson, S., 'Roux-En-Y Gastric Bypass Could Slow Progression of Retinopathy in Type 2 Diabetes: A Pilot Study'. Obesity Surgery 25, no. 5 (May 2015): 777-81. doi:10.1007/s11695-014-1476-7.

Nyhsen, C.M., Lawson, C. and Higginson, J., 'Radiology Teaching for Junior Doctors: Their Expectations, Preferences and Suggestions for Improvement'. Insights into Imaging 2, no. 3 (June 2011): 261–66. doi:10.1007/s13244-010-0052-5.

#### LETTERS, CASE REPORTS & TECHNICAL NOTES

Lwazi, S., Wates, E. and Higginson, J., 'Bony Cystic Lesion with Associated Submandibular Lymphadenopathy on a Background of Breast Carcinoma: An Unexpected Case of Cervicofacial Actinomycosis'. BMJ Case Reports 13, no. 4 (April 2020): e232850.

doi:10.1136/bcr-2019-232850.

Higginson, J., McMillan, K., Mustafa, E.M. and Grew, N., 'Use of the Superficial Inferior Epigastric Vein as an Unusual Interpositional Vein Graft'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 8 (October 2018): 761-62. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.07.001.

Wates, E., Higginson, J., Kichenaradjou, A. and McVeigh, K., 'A Severe Deep Neck Odontogenic Infection Not Prioritised by the Emergency Department Triage System and National Early Warning Score'. BMJ Case Reports, 7 May 2018, bcr-2018-224634.

doi:10.1136/bcr-2018-224634.

2016

Higginson, J., Nugent, M., and Robinson, C.M., 'Should We Test for High-Risk Human Papilloma Virus in Patients with Oral Dysplasia?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 54, no. 5 (June 2016): 590–91. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.04.016.

#### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

2018

2019

2019

2019

2019

2019

2018

2018

2017

Higginson J., Praveen P., Martin T., Parmar S. (2018) 'Reconstruction in the Oral Cavity: When and How.' In: Vermorken J., Budach V., Leemans C., Machiels J.P., Nicolai P., O'Sullivan B. (eds) Critical Issues in Head and Neck Oncology. (2018) Springer, Cham.

doi:10.1007/978-3-319-98854-2\_7

#### Published Abstracts

Payne, K., **Higginson, J.**, McCaul, J., Sharma, N., Mehanna, H. and Nankivell, P., 'Prognostic Biomarkers in Oral Epithelial Dysplasia: A Systematic Review'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e58–59. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.169

Higginson, J., Mawji, S., Dattani, A., Barnard, N. and McVeigh, K., 'Malignant Melanoma of the Head and Neck: Does Subsite of Origin Affect Prognosis?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e100. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.290.

Ali, M., Mustafa, E.M., **Higginson, J.** and Sharp, I., 'Operative Procedure Code (OPCS) Consistency and Its Implication on Theatre Efficiency at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Birmingham'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e6–7. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.009.

Wates, E., Ria, B., Samara, E. and **Higginson, J.**, 'Urgent Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery in the Pregnant Patient: A Review of the Literature'. International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 48 (May 2019): 70. doi:10.1016/j.ijom.2019.03.214.

Wates, E., Tan, S., **Higginson, J.** and McVeigh, K., 'An Incomplete DNACPR Form for a Palliative Head and Neck Oncology 25-Year-Old: Was It Valid?' International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 48 (May 2019): 85. doi:10.1016/j.ijom.2019.03.258.

Jones, F., **Higginson, J.** and Mattine, S., 'Clinical Photography: Are We Obtaining Appropriate Consent?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 10 (December 2018): e4–5.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.10.017.

Mawji, S., **Higginson**, J., Chaggar, J., Venkatasami, M. and Green, J., 'Orthognathic Surgery: A Bibliometric Analysis of the Evidence Base'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 10 (December 2018): e45. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.10.134.

Chouhan, R., **Higginson, J.,** and Martin, T., 'Confidential Image Transfer: An Ethico-Legal Dilemma'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 55, no. 10

(December 2017): e65. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2017.08.304.

Higginson, J., Chowlia, H., Martin, T., Praveen, P. and Parmar, S., 'The Use of Interpositional Vein Grafts for Free Flap Reconstruction in a Tertiary Head and Neck Unit'. Head & Neck 39, no. Si (May 2017): E71.

doi:10.1002/hed.24820.

2017

2017

2016

2012

2017

2016 2016

2014

Virdi, M, Higginson, J., Praveen, P., Martin, T. and Parmar, S., 'Are Fascia-Only ALT Flaps More Likely To Develop Donor Site Seroma?' Head & Neck 39, no. Si (May 2017): E159-60. doi:10.1002/hed.24820.

> Higginson, J., Bartram, A. and Nugent, M., 'Cutting It Fine: A Re-Audit of Surgical Resection Margins And Timing of Pathology Reports'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 54, no. 10 (December 2016): e76-77. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.11.036.

> Higginson, J., Gunasekaran, S. and Jose, J., 'Day Case Septoplasty: Ensuring Quality within Our Teaching Hospital'. International Journal of Surgery 10, no. 8 (2012): S33.

doi:10.1016/j.ijsu.2012.06.174.

### Conferences and Courses Attended

Data Analysis for Metabolic Profiling, Imperial College London. 2020 EHNS Head and Neck Robotic Surgery Symposium, Royal College of Physicians, 2019 London. Restoration of Dental Implants, BioHorizons at Houston Dental Centre, Weston-2019 super-Mare. Advanced Placement of Implants, BioHorizons at Houston Dental Centre, Weston-2019 super-Mare. BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Birmingham. 2019 BAHNO Annual Scientific Meeting, Royal College of Physicians, London. 2019 Fellows in Training Conference, Sheffield. 2019 Placement of Implants Course, Sheffield. EACMFS Biennial Congress, Munich. 2018 Non-technical skills for surgeons, Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh. 2017 Head and Neck Dissection Course, Keele University. 2017 Microvascular Skills Workshop, The Griffin Institute, Northwick Park Hospital. 2017 Laser Core of Knowledge, Liverpool University.

BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Birmingham.

IAOO Congress, Bangalore.

BAHNO Annual Scientific Meeting, Royal College of Physicians, London. 2017

EACMFS Biennial Congress, London.

BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Brighton.

BAOMS JTG Conference, Glasgow (Organised and attended).

BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Liverpool. 2015

BAOMS JTG Conference, Newcastle upon Tyne (Organised and attended). 2015

ATLS reverification, Cambridge.

BAOMS JTG Conference, London.
BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Edinburgh.
BAOMS JTG Conference, Edinburgh.
ASIT Conference, Cardiff.
Art in Surgery workshop, Cardiff.
BAOMS JTG Conference, York.
ALS, Sunderland.
ATLS, Sunderland.

#### Audit

2018

2018

2018

2017

2017

2012

Re-audit of compliance with WHO peri-operative checklists in department-based Oral Surgery—submitted for presentation at BAOS 2018 Audit of compliance with documentation of consent for clinical photography in patients undergoing surgery for head and neck cancer, presented at BAOMS 2018 Auditing speech and swallowing outcomes after major head and neck cancer treatment Re-audit of information governance in clinical images, Presented at BAOMS 2017 Audit of information governance in clinical images, Presented at Pan-Birmingham OMFS audit meeting 2017 Complications in day-case septoplasty, Presented at ASIT conference 2012

### Teaching

- **Examiner—MBChB Finals** Examiner on the practical station in the OSCE for finals, May 2018. Attended training and orientation, and shadowed an experienced examiner before taking charge of the station.
- Seminar—Written Professional Communication Final Year MBChB Component, Birmingham Medical School, Dec 2017, Tutor/Assessor, leading small group teaching sessions for final year medical students, enabling and ultimately assessing their ability to write comprehensively and concisely for referrals and discharges.
- Exam Setting—Human Diseases BDS Human Disease Examination, Birmingham School of Dentistry, Aug 2017, Examiner, Attended a meeting to develop new questions for the dental student Human Diseases examination. Recieved training in MCQ setting and the Angoff process. Contributed numerous questions for use in the exam.
- Lecturer—Tumour Growth, Management & Prognosis Fourth Year BDS Lecture at Birmingham School of Dentistry, lecturing fourth year dental students on aspects of oncology, with a focus on head and neck cancer. Lecture delivered annually from 2016
- Careers Adviser—West Midlands Dental Deanery Regular speaker at careers days, advising trainees on the pathway to oral and maxillofacial surgery (2016–present).

# Leadership and Management